# Kareem Ibrahim

2/13 Main Street, Zahraa al-Maadi, Cairo, Egypt. | (+20) 100 211 5632 | kareem.ibrahim@gmail.com

#### **PROFILE**

Architect and Urban Planner with 21 years broad experience in integrated urban development; proven track record working with international organizations in program development and implementation over a range of issues including sustainable architecture, planning, housing, environment, public infrastructure, urban revitalization, architectural and urban conservation, and community development; and strong technical managerial skills in leading projects teams, budgeting, monitoring and evaluation, communication and proactive support to programs.

#### **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

# Founding Partner - Urban Development Consultant Takween Integrated Community Development - Egypt

2010-Present

Takween is an urban development firm established in 2009 in response to a growing demand for innovative urban solutions. Takween specializes in devising integrated packages in urban development and providing services and solutions to support and complement efforts tackling urban challenges.

# Responsibilities:

Team Leader and Urban Development Consultant in various projects and consultancy missions including:

- SUPPORT FOR THE LAUNCH AND MANAGEMENT OF THE TENDER FOR THE NEEDS ASSESSMENT AND ACTIVITY DESIGN STUDY FOR
  THE PROJECT "SUPPORTING EMPLOYMENT AND IMPROVING LIVING CONDITIONS IN POOR NEIGHBOURHOODS IN EGYPT"
  L'Agence Française de Développement (AFD)
- TADAMUN: THE CAIRO URBAN SOLIDARITY INITIATIVE: RESEARCH AND POLICY ADVOCACY PLATFORM ON URBAN GOVERNANCE IN THE GREATER CAIRO REGION, EGYPT
  In Partnership with the American University (Washington D.C.)
- FORGOTTEN NEIGHBORHOODS // A PARALLEL NARRATIVE: RESEARCH PROJECT ON URBAN AND SOCIOLOGICAL HISTORY OF CAIRO'S INFORMAL NEIGHBORHOODS, CAIRO, EGYPT
   In Partnership with Laboratoire Architecture, Ville, Urbanisme, Environnement (LAVUE), Paris
- PLANNING [IN] JUSTICE: INVESTIGATION OF URBAN INEQUALITY IN THE GREATER CAIRO REGION, EGYPT
   In Partnership with the American University (Washington D.C.)
- VALORISATION AND ADAPTIVE REUSE PLAN FOR BAB AL-AZAB AREA, THE CITADEL, HISTORIC CAIRO, EGYPT World Heritage Centre (WHC) - UNESCO
- PROJECTS IDENTIFICATION STUDY FOR URBAN RENEWAL AND DEVELOPMENT IN THE SOUTHERN MEDITERRANEAN REGION, URBAN PROJECTS FINANCE INITIATIVE (UPFI), EGYPT URBACONSULTING (France), Grope CAMU (France) for the Union for the Mediterranean (UpM)
- RESEARCH STUDY ON PROMOTION OF PARTICIPATORY URBAN GOVERNANCE IN EGYPT, CAIRO, EGYPT Norwegian Peacebuilding Resource Centre (NOREF)
- SAFE CITIES FOR WOMEN AND GIRLS PROJECT, THE URBAN DEVELOPMENT COMPONENT, CAIRO, EGYPT Un Women
- Upgrading of Public Open Space with Syrian Refugees and Local Residents,  $6^{\text{TH}}$  of October City, Egypt UNHCR
- STUDY ON URBAN 'FROZEN ASSETS' IN HISTORIC CAIRO, EGYPT World Heritage Centre (WHC) - UNESCO
- HOUSING REHABILITATION STUDY URBAN REGENERATION PROJECT FOR HISTORIC CAIRO World Heritage Centre (WHC) UNESCO
- PREFEASIBILITY STUDY FOR THE IDENTIFICATION OF AN URBAN DEVELOPMENT PROJECT OR PROGRAM, CAIRO, EGYPT L'Agence Française de Developpement (AFD)
- COMPREHENSIVE URBAN DEVELOPMENT OF HISTORIC ESNA CITY CENTRE, LUXOR, EGYPT Informal Settlement Development Facility (ISDF)
- SAFEGUARDING OF HASSAN FATHY'S NEW GOURNA VILLAGE, LUXOR, EGYPT World Heritage Centre (WHC) - UNESCO

An integrated pilot initiative aiming at bringing sustainable improvements in the living conditions of one of Cairo's deprived historic inner-city districts (100,000 inhab.) through: i) upgrading housing, public buildings and open spaces; and ii) social and economic development of the local community, as two complementary goals.

#### Responsibilities:

- Plan, lead and coordinate the efforts of 4 programs (20 architects, planners and social workers), consultants
  and contractors to develop and implement a comprehensive urban revitalization strategy including urban
  design and planning schemes to conserve the built environment and improve the quality of public life;
- Establish a sustainable housing mechanism and oversee the rehabilitation/construction of 90 buildings through the housing rehabilitation program, selected in 2008 by UN-Habitat as an international Best Practice, to improve housing responsive to local needs through community participation;
- Oversee an Urban Planning Unit, whose primary role is to develop and implement an Urban Conservation Plan for the southern section of Historic Cairo, (listed as a World Heritage Site in 1979) in collaboration with the Department for Urban Projects of the Cairo Governorate, and the local Municipality;
- Upgrade infrastructure and streetscape of 5 major public spaces (2 kilometers length) to establish visitors' routes connecting vibrant community nodes and key monuments to support the district's socioeconomic development through responsible tourism and access to Al-Azhar Park, the area's main attraction;
- Design, construction, rehabilitation and adaptive-reuse of 4 key new developments and 19<sup>th</sup> Century buildings in a historic context to accommodate community public services: early childhood development, vocational training, life skills development, besides administrative, residential, retail and visitors' facilities;
- Formulate multi-year strategies, programs and budgets; identify areas of interventions; oversee acquisition of properties; cooperate with other cultural heritage organizations; approach funding agencies; write grant proposals; interface with governmental agencies; and follow up attaining required permits and approvals.

# Project Manager, AL-DARB AL-AHMAR HOUSING REHABILITATION PROGRAM Aga Khan Trust for Culture - Egypt

2001-2005

- Leading the project team, consultants and contractors towards the rehabilitation of 22 buildings through
  providing the occupants with access to grants, microcredit, and technical and administrative support;
- Planning multi-year budgets and detailed implementation plans in addition to managing the program's financial, technical and social aspects including approval of design packages and construction works;
- Overseeing participatory design sessions with residents and capacity building of different stakeholders.

# Architect/Planner, Conservation Planning in the Aslam Mosque Neighborhood Aga Khan Trust for Culture - Egypt

1998-2001

- Preparing, within a multi-disciplinary team, a physical and socioeconomic revitalization plan for a historic neighbourhood in al-Darb al-Ahmar including: i) architectural surveys and documentation; and ii) proposing conservation measures, intervention plans, and architectural designs for various interventions.

# **Architect,** Conservation Programme for the Eastern Ayyubid Wall of Cairo **Aga Khan Trust for Culture - Egypt**

1997-1998

Documentation of areas of the 12<sup>th</sup> Century Eastern Ayyubid Wall for condition survey purposes.

# Architect, Technical Cooperation Office, Rehabilitation of Historic Cairo Project

Mar.-Oct. 1997

# United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) - Supreme Council of Antiquities (SCA), Egypt

 Participation, within a multi-disciplinary team, in the documentation and preparation of the urban design scheme and intervention packages of al-Mu'izz Street, the main spine of Historic Cairo.

#### Architect, Ahmad Hamid Architects, Egypt

Jan.-Feb. 1997

Design development of the Saliba Street Hotel Apartments, infill project in the context of Historic Cairo.

#### Architect, Mega Consultant Group, Egypt

1995-1997

 Design development and preparation of working drawings for Al-Gouna Primary School (Hurghada), and a Community Mosque (6<sup>th</sup> of October City) using sustainable building technologies.

#### PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES AND CONSULTANCY WORKS

Consultant, Onsite Training of Local Craftsmen and Preparation of Training Manuals Better Life Association for Comprehensive Development (BLACD), El-Minya, Egypt

Apr. 2006

Providing BLACD with sustainable tools for its Housing Improvement Project through training of craftsmen
on the use of sustainable building technologies and production of construction and design training manuals.

Consultant, Self-Help Housing Project for Local Craftsmen

2002-2003

Hanns Seidel Stiftung - The Egyptian Earth Construction Association (EECA), South Sinai, Egypt

 Participatory housing design and provision of technical support to local craftsmen in fields of design, and production of sustainable building materials and technologies.

**Consultant,** Training on the Production of Compressed Earth Blocks (CEBS) **EECA,** Al-Tur, South Sinai, Egypt

Jun. 2003

- Lecturing and onsite training for a group of architects on the design and production of CEBs.

Project Architect, Participatory Design and Construction of an Environmental Center
The Coptic Evangelical Organization for Social Services (CEOSS) - EECA, Beni Suef, Egypt

2000-2003

 Design and construction of an environmentally responsive building using local materials, sustainable building technologies, and local craftsmen in participation with community members.

Consultant, Training on the Production of (CEBs), AL-Salib Church Conservation Project Anba Shenouda Monastery (Naqada Coptic Church) - EECA, Qenna, Egypt

Nov. 2001

- Participation in the onsite training for the project team in collaboration with the EECA.

Chairman, THE EGYPTIAN EARTH CONSTRUCTION ASSOCIATION (EECA)

1999-2001

 NGO founded in 1997 with the aim to implement and disseminate sustainable building technologies in Egypt. Activities include fund raising and implementation of various activities.

Founding Member, THE EGYPTIAN EARTH CONSTRUCTION ASSOCIATION (EECA)

1997

#### **DESIGN COMPETITIONS**

Progressive Schools Design Competition, BASIC SCHOOL, REMOTE DESERT AREAS, EGYPT

Nov. 2000

Design scheme for an environmentally and culturally responsive basic school (with group of 4 architects),
 [Organized by the Egyptian Organization for Educational Buildings] First Prize

Competition for Preparing the Planning Concept of Toshka New City, ASWAN, EGYPT

Jul. 1999

- Preparation of the City's Master Plan, detailed urban design, and housing models for a district of 20,000 inhabitants (in collaboration with the EECA), [Organized by the General Organization for Physical Planning]

Third Prize (shared with al-Dahan/Farid Company), the first and second prizes were withheld.

Housing Models Design Competition, 6<sup>TH</sup> OF OCTOBER CITY, EGYPT

Apr. 1997

- Housing models within a matrix of building patterns and urban framework, [Organized by SODIC] First Prize

# PUBLISHED WORKS

Contributions to Aga Khan Trust for Culture reports, grant proposals and publications including:
Conservation Planning in the Aslam Mosque Neighbourhood, 1999; Al-Darb al-Ahmar Regeneration Project: A
Strategy for Upgrading and Investment, 2005; Al-Darb Al-Ahmar Solidarity Project (Proposal for DFID), 2007;
Strengthening of Al-Darb Al-Ahmar Community Development Corporation (Proposal for Ford Foundation), 2008

**Contemporary Observations of al-Darb al-Ahmar** [Book Section] / auth. El-Rashidi Seif and Ibrahim Karim // Living in Historic Cairo: Past and Present in an Islamic City / book auth. Daftary Farhad, Fernea Elizabeth and Nanji Azim. - Seattle, WA: University of Washington Press, 2010. - pp. 172-179.

**Extract from a Diary: Marginal Notes on the Soft Dialectics of Historic Cairo** [Book Section] / auth. Ibrahim Kareem // Cairo contested: governance, urban space, and global modernity / ed. Singerman Diane. - Cairo: American University in Cairo Press, 2009.

**The Experience of al-Darb al-Ahmar Revitalization Project** [Conference] / auth. Ibrahim Kareem // Urban Heritage Agenda for Addis Ababa / ed. Aboukorah Omnia, Wiebusch Monika and Coetzee Sam. - Addis Ababa: Addis Ababa City Government and GTZ, 2009. - pp. 20-25.

**Transformation of the historic city of Cairo in the 2030 perspective** [Conference] / auth. Bianca Stefano, Ibrahim Kareem and El Rashidi Seif // Medinas 2030: international conference on the revitalisation of historic cities in Southern Mediterranean. - Venice: [s.n.], 2008.

**2008** Best Practices Database: Al-Darb Al-Ahmar Housing Rehabilitation Programme [Online] / auth. Ibrahim Kareem and Khalifa Haitham // UN-HABITAT Web site. - 2008. - October 7, 2009. - http://www.unhabitat.org/bestpractices/2008/mainview04.asp?BPID= 2051.

Housing rehabilitation: towards building community responsibility [Conference] / auth. Ibrahim Kareem // 1st Euro-Mediterranean regional conference: traditional Mediterranean architecture, present and future. - Barcelona: Col·legi d'Aparelladors i Arquitectes Tècnics de Barcelona pour le consortium RehabiMed, 2007. - pp. 261-263.

# LECTURES, PRESENTATIONS AND EVENTS

LECTURES, PRESENTATIONS AND EVENTS	
Reflections on the World Town Planning Day, Low Carbon Economy: Planning for a Low Carbon City [Dialogue Forum], InWEnt/BMZ, Cape Town, South Africa	Nov. 2009
<b>Al-Darb al Ahmar: Inner City Rehabilitation,</b> Strategic Planning + Sustainable Urban Development Cairo [Colloquium], KATE/University of Stuttgart, Stuttgart, Germany	Jul. 2009
<b>Planning for Low Carbon Cities,</b> Towards a Low Carbon Economy: Prospects for a long-term dialogue, climate and energy in cities [Workshop], InWEnt - BMZ, Berlin, Germany	Dec. 2008
<b>Quick Observations on Cairo's Urban Dualities,</b> Cities: Understanding Socio-cultural Transformations [Workshop], AKU-ISMC/Istanbul Bilgi University, Istanbul, Turkey	Oct. 2008
Cairo: Urban Rehabilitation, [Lecture], City of Stuttgart, Stuttgart, Germany	Jul. 2007
<b>Planning for 'Quality' in Low Cost Housing and Low Cost Housing Finance,</b> Towards Low Cost Housing [Conference], HBNRC, Cairo, Egypt	May 2007
Cairo: Revitalizing a Historic Metropolis (with S. El-Rashidi), Cairo: Urban Reviews [Exhibition], ifa/GTZ/Goethe institute/Townhouse Gallery, Cairo, Egypt	Feb. 2007
Urban Regeneration in the Darb al-Ahmar district: Integration of the Artisans' Aspects, Rehabilitation and Artisans [Training Course], RehabiMed, Cairo, Egypt	Feb. 2006
<b>Al-Darb Al-Ahmar Experience</b> (with W. Mayer), Eschborn Dialogue 2005: Designing Tomorrow's Cities [Expert Dialogue], GTZ, Frankfurt, Germany	Jun. 2005
<b>Urban Revitalization in Cairo,</b> Sustainable Urban Development in Cairo and Stuttgart: Approaches for Good Sister City Development Partnership [Expert Dialogue], KATE, Stuttgart, Germany	Jul. 2004
PROFESSIONAL TRAINING	
GIS Fundamentals, QSIT-ESRI NEA Training Centre, Cairo, Egypt	Jul. 2009
Sharing Conservation Decisions, ICCROM, Rome, Italy	Nov. 200
Strategic Direction, IMI, Hurghada, Egypt	Nov. 200
Effectively Managing Change, IMI, Cairo, Egypt	Aug. 2007
Microsoft Project, ITE Corporation, Cairo, Egypt	Mar. 200
Documentation of Vernacular Architecture, FIME - EECA, Harraneyya, Giza, Egypt	Dec. 2002
Use of Lime Mortars and Plasters in Conservation Projects, Ecole D'Avignon, Cairo, Egypt	Oct. 200
BASIN Awareness Seminar on Appropriate Building Technologies, BASIN - AEA, Inshas, Egypt	Sep. 199
EDUCATION	
Ph.D. Candidate, Urban Planning, STÄDTEBAU INSTITUT, UNIVERSITY OF STUTTGART, GERMANY	2012 - 2010
<b>B.Sc., Architecture,</b> FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, CAIRO UNIVERSITY, EGYPT Cumulative rate of appreciation: <b>Very Good</b> (78.02%) and project grade: <b>Very Good</b> .	1999
Elective Courses: - Housing in Developing Countries - Building Technology - Urban and Environmental Conservation - Community Development	

#### SKILLS

**Languages:** <u>Arabic:</u> mother tongue, <u>English:</u> fluent written and spoken, <u>French:</u> fair written and spoken.

Computer Skills: AutoCAD, 3D ArchiCAD, Adobe Photoshop, InDesign, PageMaker, MS Project, MS Office.

### **Organizational Skills:**

- Project / program management - Leadership and team building - Strategic planning

- Negotiation and conflict resolution

- Fund raising and proposal writing - Financial management

- Research design and conceptualization

- Training and capacity building

- Reporting and communication

# PERSONAL PROFILE

Date of Birth: December 8<sup>th</sup>, 1972 Nationality: Egyptian Marital Status: Married Military Status: Exempted

# REFERENCES

References available on request